Every summer, my family and I travel across the world,
كل صيف، أسافر مع عائلتي عبر العالم
3,000 miles away
3000 ميل
to the culturally diverse country of India.
إلى دولة مختلفة حضارياً و هي الهند.
Now, India is a country infamous for its scorching heat and humidity.
حالياً، الهند هي دولة غير مشهورة بالحرارة الشديدة و الرطوبة.
For me, the only relief from this heat is to drink plenty of water.
بالنسبة لي، شرب الكثير من المياه هو الحل.
Now, while in India,
عندما نكون في الهند،
my parents always remind me to only drink boiled or bottled water,
دائماً ما يذكرني والداي بشرب مياة مغلية أو معبأة.
because unlike here in America,
لأنه على عكس الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية
where I can just turn on a tap and easily get clean, potable water,
حيث يمكنني فتح الصنبور والحصول على مياه نظيفة صالحة للشرب
in India, the water is often contaminated.
في الهند، عادةً ما تكون المياه ملوثة.
So my parents have to make sure
و لذلك على والداي أن يحرصا
that the water we drink is safe.
أن المياه التي نشربها آمنة.
However, I soon realized
و لكنني لاحظت بعد ذلك
that not everyone is fortunate enough
أنه ليس كل الناس محظوظين بما يكفي
to enjoy the clean water we did.
ليستمتعوا بمياه نظيفة مثلنا.
Outside my grandparents' house in the busy streets of India,
خارج منزل جدي في شارع مزدحم بالهند،
I saw people standing in long lines
رأيت أناساً يقفون في صفوف طويلة
under the hot sun
تحت الشمس الحارقة
filling buckets with water from a tap.
يملؤون دلاء بالمياه من صنبور.
I even saw children,
رأيت أطفالاً
who looked the same age as me,
يبدون في مثل عمري
filling up these clear plastic bottles
يملؤون زجاجات المياه الشفافة
with dirty water from streams on the roadside.
بمياه قذرة من ينابيع بجانب الطريق.
Watching these kids
مشاهدة هؤلاء الأطفال
forced to drink water
المجبرين على شرب مياه
that I felt was too dirty to touch
أقذر من أن ألمسها
changed my perspective on the world.
غيرت وجهة نظري عن العالم.
This unacceptable social injustice
هذا الظلم الاجتماعي غير المقبول
compelled me to want to find a solution
أجبرني على أن أرغب في إيجاد حل
to our world's clean water problem.
لمشكلة المياه النظيفة في كوكبنا.
I wanted to know why these kids lacked water,
أردت أن أعرف لماذا كانت المياه تنقص هؤلاء الأطفال
a substance that is essential for life.
بالرغم من أنها من ضروريات الحياة.
And I learned that we are facing
و تعلمت أننا نواجه
a global water crisis.
أزمة مياه عالمية.
Now, this may seem surprising,
و هذا قد يبدو مفاجئاً
as 75 percent of our planet is covered in water,
لأن 75 % من كوكبنا تغطيه المياه،
but only 2.5 percent of that is freshwater,
و لكن 2.5 % فقط من هذه المياه عذبة،
and less than one percent of Earth's freshwater supply
و أقل من 1 % من مخزون الأرض من المياه العذبة
is available for human consumption.
متاح للاستهلاك البشري.
With rising populations,
و مع الزيادة السكانية
industrial development and economic growth,
و التطور الصناعي و النمو الإقتصادي،
our demand for clean water is increasing,
الطلب على المياه النظيفة يزداد،
yet our freshwater resources are rapidly depleting.
و لكن مصادرنا من المياه العذبة يتم استنفادها سريعاً
According to the World Health Organization,
وفقاً لمنظمة الصحة العالمية،
660 million people in our world
660 مليون شخص على كوكبنا
lack access to a clean water source.
ينقصهم الحصول على مصدر مياه نظيفة.
Lack of access to clean water is a leading cause of death
عدم الحصول علي مياه نظيفة سبب أساسي لموت
in children under the age of five in developing countries,
العديد من الأطفال تحت سن الخامسة في الدول النامية.
and UNICEF estimates that 3,000 children
ووفق تقدير اليونيسيف، 3000 طفل
die every day from a water-related disease.
يموتون يومياً بسبب أمراض متعلقة بالمياه غير النظيفة.
So after returning home one summer in eighth grade,
و لذلك بعد أن عدنا إلى المنزل في الصيف في صفي الثامن،
I decided that I wanted to combine my passion
قررت أنني أريد دمج شغفي
for solving the global water crisis
لحل أزمة المياه العالمية
with my interest in science.
مع اهتمامي بالعلم.
So I decided that the best thing to do
و لذلك قررت أن أفضل شيء يمكنني فعله
would be to convert my garage into a laboratory.
هو تحويل المرأب إلى معمل.
(Laughter)
( صوت ضحك)
Actually, at first I converted my kitchen into a laboratory,
في الواقع، لقد حوَلت مطبخي إلى معمل،
but my parents didn't really approve and kicked me out.
ولكن والداي لم يوافقا و طرداني.
I also read a lot of journal papers on water-related research,
قرأت العديد من الأوراق البحثية المتعلقة بالمياه في الجرائد،
and I learned that currently in developing countries,
و تعلمت أنه في الدول النامية حالياً،
something called solar disinfection,
يوجد شيء يسمي التنقية الشمسية
or SODIS, is used to purify water.
أو سوديس يستخدم في تنقية المياه.
In SODIS, clear plastic bottles are filled with contaminated water
في سوديس، يتم ملء زجاجات المياه الشفافة بمياه ملوثة
and then exposed to sunlight for six to eight hours.
ثم يتم تعريضها لأشعة الشمس من ست إلى ثمان ساعات.
The UV radiation from the sun
الأشعة فوق البنفسجية من الشمس
destroys the DNA of these harmful pathogens
تدمر الحمض النووي للملوثات و مسببات الأمراض
and decontaminates the water.
و تنظف المياه.
Now, while SODIS is really easy to use and energy-efficient,
بالرغم من أن سوديس سهلة الاستخدام و موفرة للطاقة
as it only uses solar energy,
لأنها تستخدم الطاقة الشمسية فقط
it's really slow,
فإنها بطيئة للغاية
as it can take up to two days when it's cloudy.
و قد تستغرق مدة يومين عندما يكون الجو غائماً.
So in order to make the SODIS process faster,
لذا من أجل جعل سوديس أسرع،
this new method called photocatalysis
هذه الطريقة الجديدة التي تسمَى التحفيز الضوئي
has recently been used.
تم استخدامها مؤخراً.
So what exactly is this photocatalysis?
ما هو التحفيز الضوئي؟
Let's break it down:
لنبسط هذه الكلمة
"photo" means from the sun,
"الضوئي" تعني من الشمس،
and a catalyst is something that speeds up a reaction.
" الحفاز" هي مادة كيميائية تسرع التفاعل الكيميائي.
So what photocatalysis is doing
لذلك ما يفعله التحفيز الضوئي هو
is it's just speeding up this solar disinfection process.
تسريع عملية السوديس.
When sunlight comes in and strikes a photocatalyst,
عندما تسطع أشعة الشمس على الحفاز الضوئي،
like TiO2, or titanium dioxide,
مثل TiO2، أو ثاني أوكسيد التيتانيوم
it creates these really reactive oxygen species,
فذلك ينتج عنه أنواع أوكسيجين تفاعلية جداً
like superoxides, hydrogen peroxide and hydroxyl radicals.
مثل الأكاسيد الفائقة، بيروكسيد الهيدروجين و مجموعة الهيدروكسيل.
These reactive oxygen species
هذه الأنواع من الأوكسجين
are able to remove bacteria and organics
تستطيع إزالة البكتيريا و العضويات
and a whole lot of contaminants from drinking water.
و العديد من الملوثات من مياه الشرب.
But unfortunately, there are several disadvantages
و لكن لسوء الحظ، هناك العديد من السلبيات
to the way photocatalytic SODIS is currently deployed.
للطريقة التي تنفذ بها السوديس حالياً.
See, what they do is they take the clear plastic bottles
ما يفعلونه هو أخذ زجاجات مياه بلاستيكية
and they coat the inside with this photocatalytic coating.
و تغطيتها من الداخل بحفاز ضوئي.
But photocatalysts like titanium dioxide
و لكن تلك الحفازات الضوئية مثل ثاني أوكسيد التيتانيوم
are actually commonly used in sunscreens
يتم استخدامها في صنع واقي الشمس
to block UV radiation.
لحجب الأشعة فوق البنفسجية.
So when they're coated on the inside of these bottles,
و لذلك عندما نستخدمهم لتغطية الزجاجات من الداخل
they're actually blocking some of the UV radiation
فإنهم يحجبون بعض الأشعة فوق البنفسجية
and diminishing the efficiency of the process.
و يقللون من كفاءة تلك العملية.
Also, these photocatalytic coatings
هذة الحفازات الضوئية أيضاً
are not tightly bound to the plastic bottle,
لا تلتصق بالزجاجة البلاستيكية
which means they wash off, and people end up drinking the catalyst.
فتمتزج بالمياة و يشربها الناس.
While TiO2 is safe and inert,
بالرغم من أن الTiO2 آمن و خامد،
it's really inefficient if you keep drinking the catalyst,
فإنه عديم الجدوى أن نظل نشرب الحفاز
because then you have to continue to replenish it,
لأنك ستحتاج إلى إعادة دهن الزجاجة
even after a few uses.
حتي بعد استخدامها مرات معدودة.
So my goal was to overcome the disadvantages
و لذلك هدفي كان التغلب على سلبيات
of these current treatment methods
طرق معالجة المياه الحالية
and create a safe, sustainable,
وإنشاء طريقة آمنة، مستدامة،
cost-effective and eco-friendly method of purifying water.
غير مكلفة و صديقة للبيئة لتنقية المياه.
What started off as an eighth grade science fair project
ما بدأته كمشروع لمعرض العلوم في الصف الثامن
is now my photocatalytic composite for water purification.
هو الآن مركب التحفيز الضوئي لتنقية المياه.
The composite combines titanium dioxide with cement.
هذا المركب يدمج ثاني أوكسيد التيتانيوم مع الأسمنت.
The cement-like composite can be formed into several different shapes,
هذا المركب الشبيه بالأسمنت يمكن تشكيله لأشكال عديدة،
which results in an extremely versatile range of deployment methods.
مما يؤدي إلى طرق استخدام عديدة و متنوعة.
For example, you could create a rod
على سبيل المثال، يمكنك تشكيل قضيب
that can easily be placed inside water bottles for individual use
يمكن وضعه بداخل زجاجات المياه بسهولة للاستخدام الشخصي
or you could create a porous filter that can filter water for families.
أو يمكننا صنع مرشح مياه لتنقية المياه للعائلات.
You can even coat the inside of an existing water tank
يمكننا أيضاً دهن خزان مياة من الداخل
to purify larger amounts of water
لتنقية كميات أكبر من المياه
for communities over a longer period of time.
للمجتمعات لفترة طويلة.
Now, over the course of this,
الآن على مر هذه الاكتشافات
my journey hasn't really been easy.
لم تكن رحلتي سهلة.
You know, I didn't have access to a sophisticated laboratory.
لم يكن لدي إمكانية الوصول لمعمل متطور.
I was 14 years old when I started,
بدأت حينما كان عمري أربع عشر عاماً،
but I didn't let my age deter me
و لم أسمح لعمري بإعاقتي
in my interest in pursuing scientific research
في اهتمامي بالبحث العلمي
and wanting to solve the global water crisis.
و إرادتي لحل أزمة المياة العالمية.
See, water isn't just the universal solvent.
المياه ليست فقط المذيب الشامل،
Water is a universal human right.
إنها حقٌ عالمي من حقوق الإنسان.
And for that reason,
و لهذا السبب،
I'm continuing to work on this science fair project from 2012
سأظل أعمل علي هذا المشروع من معرض العلوم عام 2012
to bring it from the laboratory into the real world.
لأنقله من المعمل إلى الواقع.
And this summer, I founded Catalyst for World Water,
الصيف السابق، أسست مشروع "حافز للمياه العالمية"
a social enterprise aimed at catalyzing solutions to the global water crisis.
مشروع إجتماعي يهدف إلى تحفيز الحلول لأزمة المياه العالمية.
(Applause)
( تصفيق)
Alone, a single drop of water can't do much,
قطرة مياه وحدها ليس بإمكانها فعل الكثير
but when many drops come together,
ولكن عندما تتجمع العديد من قطرات المياه
they can sustain life on our planet.
فبإمكاننا الحفاظ على الحياة على كوكبنا.
Just as water drops come together to form oceans,
مثلما تتجمع قطرات المياه لتكوين المحيطات،
I believe that we all must come together
أؤمن أننا يجب أن نتجمع سوياً
when tackling this global problem.
لنواجه تلك المشكلة العالمية.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)